

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMME

Hobart, Tasmania, Australia

\$\delta +61 466 683 552 |

\$\sum \text{toddellis.wa@gmail.com}\$

o toddellis | o tmichaelellis | stootstorm | o 0000-0002-4410-8676 | o Todd-Ellis-4

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY_____

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, but I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

University of Tasmania 2019 - 2023

- Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Bellingham, WA, USA

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

San Marcos, TX, USA

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time)

2021-02 - present

- Developing statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managing design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Designing and implementing programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff}$
- Overseeing development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

- 2019-09 present
- Overseeing multi-year project design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges

 Managing purpose platform for intersetting such as against a the fluctotistical analyses and as all data virus lighting.
- Managing custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Developing complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- Collaborating with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Sustainability Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2019-10 - 2021-02

2018-12 - 2019-05

 ${\tt University} \ {\tt of} \ {\tt Tasmania:} \ {\tt Division} \ {\tt of} \ {\tt Future} \ {\tt Students} \ ({\tt casual})$

- Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes
- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings
- Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

- Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets
- Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

APRIL 2022 TODD M. ELLIS · CURRICULUM VITAE 1 OF 2

Faculty Research Assistant

Wenatchee, WA, USA

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

2017-11 - 2018-06

- · Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- · Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- · Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

Biological Science Technician II

Ridgefield, WA, USA

2017-08 - 2017-11

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- · Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- · Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment

CONSULTING____

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity

USD\$2,500

U.S. Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate

U.S. Forest Service

USD\$2.500

HONOURS

2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research

AUD\$10,000

2021-09 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-08 Certifi-Cat of Appreciation

Australian Museum

Ten Lives Cat Centre

Frontier Development Lab

2020-08 Bushfire Data Quest 2020

AUD\$1,000

2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

AUD\$28,000 p.a.

2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

AUD\$5,000 p.a.

2018-06 Best Fish and Wildlife Science

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

2017-10 Conservation Award

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Foster Parent Hobart, TAS, Australia

TEN LIVES CAT CENTRE 2020-05 - present

Animal Handler New Braunfels, TX, USA HUMANE SOCIETY OF THE NEW BRAUNFELS AREA

2018-08 - 2019-01

Technology Tutor Wenatchee, WA, USA

2018-01 - 2018-08

Animal Handler Wenatchee, WA, USA

2018-03 - 2018-08

Geographic Information Systems Technician

Portland, OR, USA 2017-01 - 2017-11

Assistant Librarian Kelso, WA, USA

2017-01 - 2017-11

BEACON HILL FLEMENTARY SCHOOL

PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY

NORTH CENTRAL REGIONAL LIBRARY

WENATCHEE VALLEY HUMANE SOCIETY